Hi everybody and welcome to lesson 7
We're going to start by having a look at a kind of regularization called weight decay and
the issue that we came to at the end of the last lesson is that
we were training our simple dot product not all with bias and
Our lost started going down and then instead of going up again
And so we have a problem that we are
overfitting and
Remember in this case. We're using mean squared error. So
Try to recall why it is that we don't need a metric here
because
Main square error is pretty much the thing we care to care about really or we could use
In absolute error if we like, but either of those works fine as a last function
They don't have the problem of big flat areas like accuracy does replication
so what we want to do is to make it less likely that we're going to
Overfit by doing something we call reducing the capacity of the model
The capacity of the model is basically how much space does it have?
to find answers and if it can kind of find any answer anywhere those answers can include
basically memorizing the data set
So one way to handle this would be to decrease the number of latent factors
But generally speaking
Reducing the number of parameters in a model and particularly as we look at more deep learning style models
Ends up biasing the models towards very simple kind of shapes
But there's a better way to do it
Rather than reducing the number of parameters
Instead we try to force the parameters to be
Smaller unless they're really required to be big
And the way we do that is with weight decay
Weight decay is also known as l2 regularization. They're very slightly different, but we can think of them as the same thing
and what we do is we change our loss function and
specifically we change the loss function by adding to it the
sum of all the weights
squared
In fact, all of the parameters squared really should stay
Why do we do that? Well, because if that's part of the loss function
Then one way to decrease the loss would be to decrease the weights
One particular weight or all of the weights or or something like that. And so when we decrease the weights
If you think about what that would do and think about for example
The different possible
values
Of a in y equals ax squared
The larger a is for example, a is 50 you get these very narrow Peaks
in general eeeek
coefficients are going to cause
big swings big changes in the in the loss a small changes in the parameters and
When you have these kind of sharp
Peaks or valleys it means that a small change
buthe a parameter
Can make a go a small change to the input and make a big change to the loss
And so if you have if you're in that situation
Then you can basically fit all the data points close to exactly with a really complex
Jagged function with sharp changes which exactly tries to sit on
Each data point rather than finding a nice smooth surface which connects them all together
now that all goes through them all so if we limit our weights
By adding in the loss function the sum of the weights squared
Then what is going to do is it's going to fit less well on the training set because we're giving it less room to try
Anything that it wants to but we're going to hope that it would result in a better
Loss on the validation set or the test set so that it will generalize better
One way to think about this is that the loss with weight decay is just the loss plus
The some of the parameters squared times
Number we pick a hyper parameter. Sometimes it's like point 1 0.01 or 0.001 and if region
This is basically what loss with weight decay looks like in his equation
But remember when it actually comes to what's how was the loss used in stochastic gradient descent? It's used by taking its gradient
so what's the gradient of this well, if you remember back to
when you first learn calculus
It's okay. If you don't the gradient of something squared is just
Two times that's something we change from parameters to weight, which is a bit confusing though
This used wait here to keep it consistent maybe parameters is better
So the derivative of weight squared is just two times weight so in other words to add in
This term to the gradient we can just add to the gradients
Weight decay times two times weight and since weight decay is just a hyper parameter
we can just replace it with weight decay times two, so that would just give us weight decay times weight though weight decay refers to
adding on the
to the gradients
the weights times
Some hyper parameter and so that is going to try to create these kind of more shallow
less bumpy
surfaces
Do that
Simply when we call fetch will fit one cycle or whatever we can pass in a wd
Parameter and that's just this number here. So if we pass in point one
Then the training loss goes from point two nine
Point four nine that's much worse, right because we can't over fit anymore. But the valid loss goes from point eight nine zero
point eight two much better
So this is an important thing to remember for those of you that have done a lot of more traditional
statistical models
Is in kind of more traditional statistical models
we try to avoid overfitting and we try to increase generalization by decreasing the number of parameters, but
In a lot of modern machine learning and certainly the morning
We tend to instead use
regularization
Such as weight decay because it gives us more flexibility it lets us use more non-linear functions and still a boy
You know still reduces the capacity of the model
Great, so we're down to point eight two three. This is a good model. This is really actually a
very good model
and so let's dig into actually what's going on here because in our
in our architecture
remember, we basically just had or
Embedding layers or what's an embedding layer? We've described it conceptually, but let's write our own
And remember we said that an embedding layer is just a computational shortcut for doing a matrix
multiplication by a one hot and coded matrix and that that is actually the same as just
indexing into an array
So it embedding is just a
And so it's nice to be able to create our own
Versions or things that exist in pi torch and faster, so let's do that for everybody
So if we're going to create our own kind of layer, which is pretty cool
we need to be aware of something which is normally a
Layer is basically created by
Inheriting as we've discussed from module or NN module
so for example, this is an example here of a module where we've created a class called T that inherits from module and
when it's
Constructed remember that's what dunder init does. We're just going to sit. This is just a dummy little module here
We're gonna set self taught a through the number one repeated three times as a tensor
now if you remember back to
Notebook for we talked about how the optimizers in pi torch and faster. I
Rely on being able to grab the parameters attribute to find a list of all the parameters now
If you want to be able to optimize
Elf dot a you would need to it to appear in parameters. But actually there's nothing there. Why is that?
that's because pi torch does not assume that everything that's in a module is
Something that needs to be learnt the talat that it's something that needs to be learned
You have to wrap it with n n dot parameter
So here's exactly the same class, but torch dot ones, which is just a list of three three ones
This case is wrapped in an end up parameter. And now if I go
Parameters as see I have a parameter the three ones in it
And that's going to automatically call requires great underscore for us as well
We haven't had to do that for things like n n dot linear in the past because pi torch
Automatically uses an end parameter internally. So if we have a look at the parameters for something that uses an independent linear
With no bias layer, you'll see again. We have here parameter with three things in it
So we want to in general be able to create a
Parameter so something with a bio tensor with a bunch of things in and generally we want to randomly initialize them
So randomly initialize we can pass in the size
We want we can initialize a tensor of zeroes of that size and then randomly generates some normal
Normally distributed random numbers with a mean of 0 and a deviation of pointer one. No particular reason. I'm picking those numbers just
Know how this works
Things that will give us back her um at a parameters of any size we want and so
Now we're going to replace everywhere that used to say embedding. I've got to replace it with create params
Everything else here is the same in the inert under unit and then the forward is very very similar
But before as you can see, I'm grabbing the zero index column from X
That's my users and I just look it up
As you see in that user factors array
And the cool thing is I don't have to do anything with gradients myself for this
Manual embedding layer because pay torch can figure out the gradients automatically as we've discussed
but then I just got the dot product as before add on the bias as before to the sigmoid range as before and
So here's a dot product bias
without any special hi torch layers
And we fit and we get the same result
So I think that is pretty amazingly cool. We've really shown that
The embedding layer is nothing fancy is nothing magic, right? It's just indexing into an array
So hopefully that removes a bit of the mystery for you
So, let's have a look at this model that we've created and we've trained
And find out what it's learned that's already useful. We've got something we can make pretty accurate predictions with
but let's find out what those
What the model looks like?
Remember when we cut a question
Okay, let's take a question before you can look at this
What's the advantage of creating our own embedding layer over the stock PI torch one? Oh
Nothing at all
We're just showing that we can it's it's great to be able to dig under the surface
Because at some point you'll want to try doing new things
so a good way to learn to do new things is to be able to replicate things that already exist and
You can exit you understand how they work
It's also a great way to understand the foundations of what's going on is to actually create encode your own implementation
But I wouldn't expect you to use this implementation in practice
But basically it removes all the mystery
so
If you remember
we've created a learner called learn and to get to the model that's inside it you can always call learn model and
then inside that there's going to be
Automatically created for it. Well, sorry not automatically. We've created all these attributes movie factors movie bias bias and so forth
Where we can grab learn model drop movie bias
and now what I'm going to do is I'm going to sort that vector and
I'm going to print out
the first five
idols and
so what this is going to do is it's going to print out though the movies with the smallest bias and
Here they are. What does this mean? Well, it kind of means these are the five movies that people
really didn't like
But it's more than that
It's it's not only do people not like them. But if we take account of the
Genre, they're in the actors. They have you know, whatever. The latent factors are people liked them a lot less than they expected
so maybe
example people this is kind of I haven't seen any of these movies likely perhaps this is a
Sci-fi movie so people who kind of like these sci-fi movies down there so bad. They still didn't like it
Um so we can do the exact opposite which is to sort
sending and here are the top five movies and
Specifically, they're the top five my bias, right? So these are the movies
so even after you take account of the fact that
LA Confidential I have seen all of these ones. So a low confidential is a kind of a
Murder mystery cop movie I guess and people who don't necessarily like that genre or I think Guy Pearce was in it
So maybe they don't like Guy Pearce very much. Whatever people still like this movie more than they expect
So this is a kind of a nice thing that we can look inside our model and see what it's learned
now we can look out not only at the
Bias
vector
But we can also look at the factors now
There are 50 factors, which is too many to visualize so we could use a technique called pca principal components
Now this the details don't matter
But basically they're going to squish those 50 factors down to 3 and then we'll plot the top two
as you can see here and
What we see when we plot the top 2
Is we can kind of see that the movies have been and have spread out across a space of of?
Some kind of latent factors. And so if you look at the far, right?
There's a whole bunch of kind of
Big budget actually things and on the far left. There's more like cult kind of things Fargo Schindler's List
Monty Python
By the same token at the bottom. We've got some
English Patient
Perryman Harry Met Sally so kind of romance drama kind of stuff and at the top we've got
action and sci-fi kind of stuff so you can see even as though we haven't
Asked in any information about these movies
What we've seen is who likes what?
these latent factors have automatically kind of figured out a
Space or a way of thinking about these movies based on what kinds of movies people like and what other kinds of movies they like
along with those
That's really interesting to kind of try and visualize
What's going on inside?
your model
Now we don't have to do all this manually we can actually just say
Give me a collab learner
using this set of data loaders with this number of factors in this way range and it does everything we've just seen
Again about the same number. Okay. Well now you can see this is nice, right?
we've actually be able to see right underneath inside the collab liner part of the FASTA a
Application the collaborative filtering application and we can build it all ourselves from scratch
We know how to create the SGD know how to create the embedding layer. We know how to create the
Model the architecture. So now you can see, you know, we've really and build up from scratch our own version of this
So if we just type learned up model, you can see here. The names are a bit more generic
This is a user weight item weight is a bias item bias, but it's basically the same stuff we've seen before
And we can replicate the exact analyses we saw before by using this same idea. Yep
Slightly different order this time because is a bit random but
Pretty similar as well
Another interesting thing we can do is we can think about the distance between two movies
So let's grab all the movie factors
Or just pop them into a variable
And then let's pick a movie
And then let's find the
Distance
from
That movie ooh
every other movie and so one way of thinking about distance is you might recall the
Pythagorean formula or
The distance on on a on the hypotenuse of a triangle which is also the distance
We were a point on it in a Cartesian plane on a chart which is root x squared plus y squared
You might know doesn't matter if you don't but you can do exactly the same thing for
50 dimensions. It doesn't just work for two dimension
There's a
that tells you how far away a point is from another point if you if x and y are actually
differences between two movie
vectors
So then what gets interesting is
You can actually then
provide that
kind of by the
by the length to make all the lengths the same distance to find out how the angle between any two B movies and that actually
Turns out to be a really good way to compare the similarity of two things that's called cosine similarity
And so the details don't matter you can look them up if you're interested
But the basic idea here is to see that we can actually pick a movie and find the movie
That is the most similar to it
Based on these factors kind of interest ever questions. All right Oh,
What motivated learning at a 50 dimensional embedding and then using yay to reduce three versus just learning a few mention?
Oh because the purpose of this was actually to create a good model though. The the
Visualization part is normally kind of the exploration of what's going in on in your model and so with a 50
With 50 latent factors, you're going to get a more accurate
So that's one approach is this
dot product
Version there's another version we could use which is we could
create a
set of user factors and
a set of item factors and
The slight before we could look them up
But what we could then do instead of doing a dot product we could concatenate them together
into a
tensor that contains both the user and the movie factors next to each other and then we could pass them through a
simple little neural network lennier Lu linear and then sigmoid ranges before
So importantly here the first linear layer
The number of inputs is equal to a number of user factors plus the number of item factors
And the number of outputs is however many activations
we have
and
then which may be we just default to a hundred here and then the final layer will go from a hundred to one because we're
Just making one prediction and so we could create
Or call that collab and n we can instantiate that to create a model. We can create a learner and we can get
It's not going quite as well as before it's not terrible, but it's not quite as good as our dot product version
But the interesting thing here is it does give us some more flexibility
Which is that since we're not doing a dot product we can actually have a different
embedding size
For each of users versus items and actually faster
I has a simple heuristic if you call get embedding size and pass in your data loaders, it will suggest appropriate size
Embedding matrices or each of your categorical variables its each of your user and item
Enters
so that's so if we pass in
Star m's beddings that's going to pass in the user
Apple and the item
Apple which we can then pass to embedding
This is star prefix we learned about in the last class in case you forgot
So this is kind of interesting we can
You know we can see here that there's two different
Architectures we could pick from it wouldn't be necessarily obviously ahead of time, which one's going to work better?
I'm in this particular case the the simplest one the the dot product one actually turned out to work a bit better, which is interesting
this particular version here if you call collab donor and
pass use NN equals true
then what that's going to do is it's going to use this version the version with
Concatenation and the linear layers
So coli Bellona use an N equals true again
We get about the same result as you'd expect because it's just a rock-cut for this version
And it's interesting actually
We have a look at collab liner, it actually returns an object of type embedding an N
and
It's kind of cool
If you look inside the frosty air source code or use the double question mark trick to see the source code for embedding it in
You'll see it's three lines of code
How does that happen because we're using this thing called tabular model
Which we will learn about
in a moment, but basically this
Neural net version of collaborative filtering is
literally just a tabular model in which we pass no continuous variables and
I'm embedding sizes
So we'll see that in a moment
Okay, so that is
collaborative filtering and again take a look at the further research section in particular how if you finish the questionnaire and because there's some really
Important next steps you can take to push your knowledge and your skills
So let's now move to my book mine a Beulah and
we're going to look at tabular modeling and do a deep dive and
let's start by talking about this idea that we were starting to see here, which is
Embeddings and
Specifically, let's move beyond just having embeddings for users and items at embeddings for any kind of categorical variable
But really because we know an embedding is just a lookup into an array
It can handle
Any kind of discrete?
categorical data
So things like age are not discrete their continuous numerical data, but something like sex or postcode
Are categorical variables? Um, they have a certain number of discrete levels. The number of discrete levels. They have is called their
cardinality
So des haven't looked at an example of a data set that contains both categorical and continuous
Variables we're going to look at the Rossman sales competition that ran on Kegel a few years ago
and so basically what's going to happen is we're going to see a
table that contains information about
Various stores in Germany and the goal will be to try and predict how many sales there's going to be
for each day in a couple of weeks period for each store
One of the interesting things about this competition is that one of the gold medalists used
Deep learning and it was one of the earliest known
example of a state of the art deep learning a beulah model I
Mean this is not long ago
2015 or something but really this idea of creating state Athiya tabular models with deep learning has not been very common
and for not very long
You know interestingly compared to the other gold medalists in this competition
The folks that used deep learning used a lot less feature engineering and a lot less domain expertise
And so they wrote a paper called entity embeddings of categorical variables
in which they basically
described the exact thing that you saw in the in notebook eight the way you can think of one hot encodings as
Just being embeddings. You can catenate them together and you can put them through a couple of layers
They call them dense layers. We've got the Millennial layers and create a neural network out of there
so this is really
neat, you know it's kind of simple and obvious in hindsight trick and
They actually did exactly what we did in the paper
which is to look at the results of the trained embeddings, and so for example
they had an embedding matrix for
Regions in Germany
Because there was what there wasn't really metadata about this
These were just learnt in bedding was just like we learnt embeddings about movies
And so then they just created just like we did before a chart where they popped each region
According to I think probably a PCA
Of their embeddings and then if you circle the ones that are close to each other in blue
you'll see that they're actually close to each other in Germany and ditto for red and it over green and
Then here's the brown
so this is like
Pretty amazing is the way that we can see that it's kind of learnt something about what Germany looks like
Based entirely on the purchasing behavior of people in those states
something else they did was to look at every straw and
they looked at the
distance between stores in
practice like how many kilometers away they are and
Then they looked at the distance between stores in terms of their embedding distance
Just like we saw in the previous notebook and there was this very strong correlation that stores that were close to each other
physically
Ended up having close
embeddings as well even as though
Location of these stores in physical space was not part of the model
Ditto with days of the week so the days of the week for another
Embedding and the days of the week that were next to each other ended up next to each other in
Embedding space and ditto for months of the year. So pretty fascinating they're way
kind of
information about the world ends up captured just by looking at browning embeddings, which as we know are just
index lookups into an array
So the way we then combine these categorical variables with these embeddings with continuous variables
What was done in both the?
Entity embedding paper that we just looked at and then also described in more detail
By Google when they described how their recommendation system in Google Play works
this is from Google's paper is they have the categorical features that go through the embeddings and then there are continuous features and
Then all the embedding results and the continuous features are just concatenated together
Into this big concatenated table that then goes through in this case three layers of a neural net and interestingly
they also take the kind of
Collaborative filtering bit and do the dot product as well and combine the two so they use both of the
Bricks were used in the previous notebook and combine them together
So
That's the basic idea. We're going to be seeing or
proving beyond just collaborative filtering which is
Just two categorical variables to as many categorical and as many continuous variables as we like
But before we do that
let's take a step back and think about other approaches because as I mentioned the idea of
Deep learning is a kind of a best practice for tabular data. It is still pretty new and it's still kind of controversial
It's certainly not always the case but it's the best approach
So when we're not using deep learning, what would we be using?
Well, what would probably be using is something called an ensemble of decision trees and the two most popular are random forests
and
Gradient boosting machines or something them alone
so basically between multi-layered neural networks learnt with SGD and ensembles of decision trees that kind of covers the vast majority of
Approaches that you're likely to see for tabular data. And so we're going to make sure we cover them both us today. In fact
So although deep learning is nearly always clearly superior for stuff like images and audio and
Natural language texts, these two approaches tend to give somewhat similar results a lot of the time
for
Tabular data, so let's take a look some, you know, you really should generally try both and see which works best for you
for each problem you look at
Why does the range go from zero to 5.5 if the maximum I've
That's a great question. Um, the reason is if you think about it for sigmoid it's
Actually impossible for a sigmoid to get all the way to the top or all the way to the bottom. There's a asymptotes
So no matter how far how big your X is
Can never quite get to the top or no matter how small it is. It can never quite get
So if you want to be able to actually predict a rating of five, then you need to use something higher than five your maximum
Our embeddings used only for highly cardinal categorical variables or is this approach you general or low
cardinality can unuse one-hot encode a
Remind you cardinality is the number of great levels and variable and
That
An embedding is just a computation or shortcut or oh one hot encoding
so there's really no reason to use a one hot encoding because it's
As long as you have more than two levels
It's always going to be more memory and lower and give you exactly mathematically the same thing and if there's just two levels
Then it is basically identical so there isn't really any reason not to use
Thank you for those great questions
Um
Okay, so
One of the most important things about decision tree ensembles is that at the current state of the technology they do provide
faster and easier ways of interpreting the model
I think that's rapidly improving for deep learning models on tabular data, but that's where we are right now
They also require rest less hyper parameter tuning. So they're easier to kind of get right the first time. So my first approach
analyzing a dataset is always an ensemble of decision trees and specifically I pretty much always start with a random forest because it's just so
reliable
Yes
Your experience for highly imbalanced as such fraud or medical data
What usually best out of rainforest XG boost or neural network? Um, I'm not sure that
the
Weather the data is balanced or unbalanced is a key reason for choosing one of those about the others
I would try all of them and see which works best
So the exception to the guideline about start with decision tree ensembles as your first thing to try would be if there's some very high
Cardinality categorical variables then they can be a bit difficult to get to work really well in decision tree ensembles
Or if there's something like most importantly that's like plain text data or image data or audio data or something like that and
Then you'll definitely kind of need to use a neural net in there
But you could actually ensemble it with a random forest as we'll see
Okay, oh really we're going to need to understand how our decision tree ensembles work
So pay torch isn't a great choice for decision tree ensembles they're really designed for gradient based methods and
Random forests and decision tree growing are not really gradient based methods in the same way
So instead we're going to use a library called scikit-learn
Referred to as SK learn as a module
Scikit-learn does a lot of things
And we're only going to touch on a tiny piece of them if we need to do to train
decision trees and random forests
We've already mentioned before was McKinney's book. Also a great book for understanding more about circuit learn
So the data set for learning about
Decision tree ensembles is going to be another data set. It's going to it's called the
Blue Book for bulldozes data set and it's a cackle competition
So Kaggle competitions are fantastic. They are
Machine learning competitions where you get interesting data sets you get feedback on whether your approach is any good or not?
You can see on a leaderboard what approaches are working best and then you can read blog posts from the winning contestants
sharing tips and tricks
it's certainly not a
substitute for actual
Practice doing end-to-end
Data science projects but for becoming good at creating predictive models that are predictive
It's a really fantastic resource highly recommended and you can also submit to old most old competitions
To see how you would have gone without having to worry about you know
the kind of stress of like whether people will be looking at your results because they're not
Publicized or published if you do that
Is it yes, it's a question you comment on real time applications of random forests. I
Experience they tend to be too slow for real-time use cases like a recommender system
Neural network is much faster when run on the right hardware
Let's get to that once in go - shall we?
Now you can't just
Download an entire
cackled datasets using the entire data thing that we have in first AI so you actually have to sign up to Kegel and
Then follow these instructions
for how to download
Data from Kegel make sure you replace creds here with what it describes
You need to get a special API code and then run this one time to put that up on your server
and now you can
Use Kegel to download data using the API
so
After we do that, we're going to end up with a bunch of as you see CSV files
So let's take a look at this data
Well the main data
The main table is trained on CSV
remember that's comma separated values and
The training set contains information such as unique identify over say all the using unique identify over machine
Sale price say old date. So what's going on here is one row of the data
Represents a seeing a seal of a single piece of heavy machinery like a bulldozer
At an auction. So it happens at a date as a price. It's of some particular piece of equipment and so forth
So if we use pandas again to read in a CSV file
Let's combine training and valid together
We can then look at the columns to see
There's a lot of columns there and many things which I don't know. What the hell they mean like blade
extension and pad type and ride control
but the good news is
We're going to show you a way that you don't have to look at every single column and understand what they mean
And random forests are going to help us with that as well
So once again, we're going to be seeing this idea that models can actually help us with data understanding and data cleanup
One thing we can look at is ordinal columns and good place to look at that now if there's things there that you know are
discrete values that have some order like product size
It has medium and small and large medium and many these should not be in
You know alphabetical order or some random order they should be in this
Specific order right? They they have they have a specific ordering
so we can
use
But as type to turn it into a categorical variable and then we can say set categories ordered equals true
To basically say this is an ordinal column
So it's got discrete values, but we actually want to define what the order of the classes are
We need to choose which is the dependent variable
and we do that by looking on cattle and cowgirl will tell us that the thing we're meant to be predicting is sale price and
Actually specifically they'll tell us the thing
we're meant to be predicting is the log of sale price because root mean squared log error is them is the
What we're actually gonna be judged on in the competition where we take the log
So we're not going to replace sale price with its log and that's what we'll be using for now on
So a decision tree ensemble
Requires decision trees. Well, let's start by looking at decision trees. So a decision tree
In in in this case is a something that asks a series of binary
that is yes or no questions about data so such as is
Somebody less integrated at less than 30. Yes. They are. Are they eating? Healthily? Yes, they are
And so okay, then we're going to say they're fit or unfit
So like there's an example of some arbitrary
Decision tree that somebody might have come up with it's a series of binary
Yes, and no choices and at the bottom are leaf nodes that make some prediction
Now of course
Our
Bulldozers competition. We don't know what binary questions to ask about these things. And in what order?
in order to make a prediction about sale price, so
We're doing machine learning. So we're going to try and come up with some automated way to create the questions and
There's actually a really simple procedure for doing that. You have a think about it
so if you want to kind of stretch yourself here, however, think about
What's an automatic procedure?
that you can come up with that would automatically build a decision tree where the final answer would do a
you know the difficulty better than random job of estimating the sale price of
one of these options
All right, so here's here's the approach that we could use
Look through each column of the data set. We're going to go through each of
But obviously not sale prices the dependent variable sale ID machine ID
Auctioneer year made, etc. And so one of those will be for example
product size
And so then what we're going to do is we're going to loop through
each
possible value of
product size
Large large medium medium, etc
And then we're going to do a split basically like where this comma is and we're going to see okay
Let's get all of the options of large
Equipment and put that into one group and everything that's smaller than that and put that into another group
And so that's here split the data into two groups
Based on whether they're greater than or less than that value
If it's a categorical non ordinal value a variable, it'll be just whether it's equal or not equal to that level
And then we're going to find the average sale price for each of the two groups
So for the large group, what is the average sale price for the more than large group? What was the average sale price and
That will be our model. Our prediction will simply be the average sale price for that group
And so then you can say well how good is that model if our model was just to ask a single question
With a yes/no answer put things into two groups and take the average of the group as being our prediction
And we can see how good with that model be. What would be the root means great error from that model
And so we can then say all right. How could it would it be if we
Use large better and then let's try again. What if we did large medium is a split
What if we did medium is this better?
and so in each case we can find the root mean squared error of that incredibly simple model and
then once we've done that for all of the product size levels we can go to the next column and look at
a lot usage banned and do every level of usage banned and then state your level or state and
So forth and so there'll be some variable and some split level which gives the best
Root mean squared error of this really really simple model. And so then I'll say okay, that would be our first binary decision
it gives us two groups and then we're going to take each one of those groups separately and
Great find another single binary decision
For each of those two groups using exactly the same procedure
But then we'll have four groups and then we'll do exactly the same thing again separately feature those four groups and so forth
So
Let's see what that looks like
And in fact, once we've gone through this you might even want to see if you can implement this algorithm yourself. It's not
Reveal, but it doesn't require any special coding skills. So hopefully you can find you will be able to do it
There's a few things we have to do before we can actually create a decision tree in terms of just some basic data munging
One is if we're going to take advantage of dates
We actually want to call faster eyes add date part function and what that does as you see after we call it
As it creates a whole different a bunch of different bits of metadata from that data
So all year there are months so a week say all day and so forth
So sale date of itself doesn't have a whole lot of information
Directly, but we can pull a lots of different information out of it
And so this is an example of something called feature engineering
Which is where we take some peace some piece of data and we try to grab create lots other lots of other pieces of data
From it. So is this particular day at the end of a month or not at the end of a year or not?
and so forth but
That handle states
There's a bit more cleaning. We want to do and faster UI provides some things to make meaning easier
We can use the tabular pandas class. We create a tabular data set Anders
and
specifically we're going to use to
fabula processes or tabular procs a tabular processor is basically just to transform and
Racine transforms before so go back and remind yourself where the transform is
Except it's just slightly different. It's like three lines of code if you look at the code for it
it's actually going to modify the object in place rather than
creating a new object
And giving it back to you and that's because often these tables of data are kind of really big and we don't want to waste
lots of RAM
And it's just gonna run the transform once and save the result rather than doing it
Lazily when you access it, but for the same reason we just want to make this a lot faster
so
Just think of them as transforms really. So one of them is called category FA and category fire is going to replace a column
With numeric categories using the same basic idea of like a vocab like we've seen before
Bill missing is going to find any
Columns with missing data and it's going to fill in the missing data with the median of the data and create a new column
Your boolean column which is set to true for anything that was missing though
These two things is basically enough to get you to a point where most of the time you'll be able to train a model
Now the next thing we need to do is think about our validation set as we discussed in lesson one
A random validation set is not always appropriate and certainly for something like predicting
Auction results it almost certainly is not appropriate because we're going to be wanting to use a model in the future
Not at some random date in the past. So the way this Kaggle
competition was set up was that that the test set the thing that you had to fill in and submit for the competition was
Two weeks of data that was after any of the training set
So we should do the same thing for validation set
we should create something which is
Where the validation set is the last couple of weeks of data?
and
And so then the training set will only be data before that. So we basically can do that by grabbing everything before
October 2011
I'll create our training and validation set based on that condition and
grabbing those bits
So that's going to spit our baiting certain validation set by date not randomly
We're also going to need to tell when you
Create a tabular pandas object
You're going to be passing in a data frame going to be passing in your tabular procs
And you also have to say what are my categorical and continuous variables?
We can use
faster use Conte cat split
We automatically split a data frame do continuous and categorical variables for you
So we can just pass those in
what what is the dependent variable you can have more than one and what are the indexes to split into training and valid and
This is a tabular object
so it's got all the information you need about the training set the validation set categorical and continuous variables and the dependent variable and
Any processes to run?
It looks a lot like a data set subject but has a dot train it has a dot valid
And so if we have a look at that show we can see
the data
But Dutch show is going to show us the kind of the string data
But if we look at but items you can see internally it's actually stored
These very compact numbers which we can use directly in a model
So first ideas basically got us to a point here where we have our data into a format
I'm ready for modeling and validation sets being created
to see how these numbers
Relate to these strings we can again just like we saw last week use the classes attribute
Which is a dictionary it basically tells us the vocab
So this is how we look up for example, 6 is 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 this is compact example
That processing took takes a little while to run so you can go ahead and save the tabular object
And so then you can load it back later without having to rerun or the processing
So that's a nice kind of fast way to quickly get back up and running without having to reprocess your data
So we've done the basic data munging
We need we can now create a decision tree and in scikit-learn a decision tree where the dependent variable is. Continuous is a
decision tree regressor
Now let's start by telling it. We just want a total of four
Leaf nodes. We'll see what that means in a moment and
In scikit-learn you generally call fit
so it looks quite a lot like fast AI and you pass in your independent variables and your dependent variable and
We can grab those straight from our tabular object training set. It's not X's and
But Y and we can do the same thing for validation just to save us and typing. Okay question
you have any thoughts on what data augmentation for tabular data might look like
I don't have a great sense of data organization with nebula dater
We'll be seeing later either in this course or in the next part
Drop out and mix up and stuff like that which they might be able to do that
in later layers in
The tabular model. Otherwise, I think you'd need to think about
The semantics of the data and think about what are things you could do to change the data without changing the meaning?
Sounds like a pretty tricky
well a
Question is fastly I distinguish between ordered
categories such as low medium high and
Unordered category world bearable. I guess that that was that ordinal thing
I told you about before and all it really does is it ensures that your
Classes list has a specific order
so then these numbers actually have a specific and
As you'll see that's actually going to turn out to be pretty important for how we trained our random first
Okay, so we can create a decision tree regressor we can fit it
And then we can draw it the faster I function
and
Here is the decision tree. We just trained
And we and behind the scenes. This actually used be
Basically the exact process that we described
Back here, right? So this is where you can like try and create your own
Decision tree implementation if you're interested in stretching yourself
So we're going to use one that's already
exists and the best way to understand what it's done is to look at this diagram from top to bottom so
This first step is it says like okay the initial model it created is a model with no binary splits at all
Pacifically it's always going to predict the value 10.1 or every single row
Why is that?
well because this is the simplest possible model is to take the average of the dependent variable and
Always predict that and so this is always should be you're kind of pretty much your basic
baseline for regression
There are four hundred and four thousand seven hundred and ten
rows options that we're averaging and the mean squared error of this incredibly simple model in which there are no
Rules at all though groups at all. Just a single average is a point weight
so then the next most complex model is to take a single column a plus system and
A single binary decision is coupler system less than or equal to 0.5
through
There are 360 thousand eight hundred forty-seven
Options where it's true and forty three thousand eight hundred sixty-three where it's false and now interestingly in the false case
You can see that there are no further binary decisions. So this is called a leaf node
it's a node where this is as far as you can get and
So if your coupler system is not less than or equal to 0.5
Prediction this model makes for euro sale price is nine point two one
Versus if it's true
It's ten point to one so you can see it's actually found a very big difference here and that's why it picked
This is the first binary split and so the mean squared error for this section here is 0.12
Which is far better than we started out at 0.5
Has
360,000 in it and so it does another binary split this time is the year that this
Piece of equipment made was at less than or equal to
1991 and a half if it was if it's true
Then we get a leaf node
And the prediction is nine point nine seven means grid arrow point three seven if the value is false
We don't have a leaf node
And we have another binary split and you can see eventually we get down to here coupler system
true year made false product size false mean square error point one seven
so all of these leaf nodes of MSE s that are smaller than
that
original baseline model of just taking the mean
so this is how you can grow a
Decision tree and we only stopped here because we said max leaf knows is for one two, three. Oh
Right, and so if we want to keep training it further
We can just use a higher number. Um, there's actually a very nice
Library by Terrence park or D Treves
Which can show us exactly the same information like so and so here are the same
Leaf nodes one through three or and you can see the kind of the chart of how many are there
This is the split coupler system point five. Here are the two groups
you can see the sale price in each of the two groups and
Then here's the leaf node
And so then the second split was on year made, and you can see here
Something weirds going on with um aid there's a whole bunch of here made sit or a thousand which is obviously not a sensible
Year for a bulldozer to be made so presumably that's some kind of missing value
So when we look at their kind of the picture like this it can give us some insights about what's going on in our data
and so maybe
We should replace those thousands with
Nineteen fifty because that's you know, obviously a very very early year for a bulldozer and so we can kind of pick it arbitrarily
It's actually not really going to make any difference to the model. That's created
Because all we care about is the order because we're just doing these binary splits
That'll make it easier to look at as you can see
Here's our nineteen fifties now. And so now it's much easier to see what's going on in that binary speed
So let's now get rid of max leaf nodes and build a bigger decision tree
And then let's just for the rest of this
Notebook create a couple of real functions one to create the root mean squared error
which is just here and
Another one to take a model and some independent independent variables
predict
From the model on the independent variables and then take the root mean squared error with a dependent variable
So that's going to be our models where it means great error
So for this decision tree in which we didn't have a stopping criteria, so as many leaf nodes as you like
the models root mean squared error is
zero
So we've just built the perfect model
So this is great news, right we have built the perfect option trading system
Well, remember we actually need to check the validation set. Let's check the check Mrs
E with a validation set and oh it's worse than zero
So our training set is zero our validation set is much worse than zero
Why is that happened?
Well, one of the things that a random forest in SK learn can do is it can tell you the number of leaf nodes number?
Of leaves there are 340 1000
Data points
400,000
So in other words, we have nearly as many leaf nodes as data points
Most of our leaf nodes only have a single thing in but they're taking an average of a single thing clearly
This makes no sense at all. So what we should actually do is
pick some
Different stopping criteria and let's say okay if you got a leaf node with 25 things or less in it
don't don't split or don't split things to create a leaf node with less than 25 things in it and
Now if we fit and we look at the root mean squared error for the validation set
It's going to go down from 0.33
0.32
So the training sets got worse from zero two point two four eight. The validation sets got better and now we only have
12,000 leaf nodes
So that is much more reasonable
All right
So let's take a five-minute break and then we're going to come back and see how we get the best of both worlds
How are we going to get something which has the kind of?
flexibility to get these
You know what? We're going to get down to zero
But to get you know really deep trees
But also without overfitting and the trick will be to use something called bagging. I'll come back and talk about that in five minutes
You
Okay, so welcome back so
We're going to look at how we can get the best of both worlds as we discussed and
Let's start by having a look at what we're doing with categorical variables first of all, and so you might notice that
Obviously with categorical variables for example in collaborative filtering we had two
You know kind of think about like how many embedding levels we have
For example, if you've used other modeling tools, you might have there in Singh's with creating dummy variables stuff like that
um random forests on the whole you don't have to
The the reason is that as we've seen all of our
Categorical variables
Turned into numbers and so we can perfectly well have
Session tree binary decisions which use those particular numbers now
The numbers might not be ordered at any interesting way
But if there's a particular level
Which kind of stands out as being important it only takes two
Binary splits the split out that level into a single
You know into a single piece
So generally speaking. I don't normally worry too much about kind of encoding
Categorical variables in a special way as I mentioned I do try to
Encode ordinal variables by seeing what the order of the levels is because often as you would expect
sizes, for example
You know medium and small or gonna mean kind of next to each other and large and extra-large would be next to each other
That's good to have those as similar numbers
Having said that you can out of one hot encode a
Categorical variable if you want to using get dummies in pandas
But there's not a lot of evidence that that actually helps. There's actually that has been bought in a paper
And so I would say in general for categorical variables. Don't worry about it too much just
Use what we've shown you. You have a question
For for ordinal categorical variables. How do you deal with?
when they have like n/a or
Missing values. Where do you put that in the order?
So in first AI na missing values always appear as the first item will always be the zero index
atom and also if you get something in
The validation or test set which was a level
We haven't seen in training that will be considered to be that missing or na value as well
All right, so
What we're gonna do to try and improve our random forest is we're going to use something called bagging and this was developed
by a
retired Berkeley professor named leo breiman in 1994 and
He did a lot of great work and perhaps you could see that most of it happened after he retired
His technical report was called bagging predictors and he described how you could create multiple versions of her predictor
so multiple different models
and you could then aggregate them by averaging over the
predictions and
Specifically, um, the way he suggested doing this was to create what he called bootstrap
Replicates in other words randomly select different subsets of your data now train a model on that subset and it store it away
As one of your predictors and then do it again a bunch of times
and so each of these models is trained on a different random subset of your data and then you
To predict you predict on all of those different versions of your model and average them
and it turns out that
bagging works really well, so this the sequence of steps is basically
randomly choose some subset of rows
Where in a model?
Using that subset gave that model and then returned to step one through that a few times to train a few models
And then to make a prediction predict with all the models and take the average
That is packing and
It's very simple, but it says punishingly powerful. And the reason why is that each of these models we've trained
Although they are not using all of the data
So they're kind of less accurate than a model that use all of the data
Each of them is the errors are not correlated
You know that the errors because of using that smaller subset are not correlated with the errors of the other models
because they're random subsets and
so when you take the average of
a bunch of kind of
Errors, which are not correlated with each other
The average of those errors is zero
So therefore the average of the models
Should give us an accurate prediction of the thing. We're actually trying to predict
So as I say here's an amazing result, we can improve the accuracy of nearly any kind of algorithm by training at multiple times
About different random subsets of data and then averaging the predictions
Though then Bremen in 2001 showed a way to do this specifically for decision trees
Where not only did he randomly choose a subset of rows for each model?
But then for each binary split he also randomly selected a subset of columns
and this is called the random forest and
It's perhaps the most widely used most practically important machine learning method and astonishingly
simple
To create a random forest regressor you use SK Loans random first aggressor
if you pass n drops minus one, it will use all of the CPU cores that you have to run as fast as possible n
Estimators says how many trees how many models to train?
Max sample says how many rows to use?
randomly chosen rows to use in each one max features is how many
randomly chosen columns to use for each binary split point
Min samples leaf is the stopping criteria
And we'll come back to so here's a little function that will create a random first regressor and fit it through
Some set of independent variables and a dependent variable
So we can give it a few
default values and create a random forest and
train and
Our validation set our MSE is 0.23
If we compare that
of what we had before
You
We had
Point three - so dramatically better
By using a random forest
Um, so
So what's happened when we
Called random first aggressor is it's just using that decision tree builder that we've already seen but it's building
multiple versions with these different random subsets and for each binary split it does it's also
randomly selecting a subset of columns
And then when we create a prediction, it is averaging the predictions of each of the trees
and as you can see, it's giving a really great result and one of the amazing things we'll find is that
It's gonna be hard for us to improve this very much, you know
The kind of the default starting point tends to turn out to be pretty great
The the SK learn documentation
Crease the number of estimators
out as the
accuracy improve error rate proofs or different max features levels
And in general the more trees you add
The more accurate your model there the it's not going to overfit right because it's averaging more of these
These week models more of these models that are trained on subsets of the data so train as many users many estimators as you like
Really just a case of how much time do you have? And whether you kind of reach a point where it's not really improving anymore
You can actually get at the underlying decision trees in a model in a random first model using estimators underscore
so with a list comprehension we can call predict on each individual tree and
So here's an array an umpire array containing the predictions from each individual tree for each row in our data
So if we take the mean
Across the 0 axis Rockette
Exactly the same number as remember
First does is it takes the main?
of the trees predictions
So one cool thing we could do is we could look at
the 40
Estimators we have and grab the predictions or the first eye
Those trees and take their mean
Then we can find the root mean square error
In other words here is the accuracy when you've just got one tree
root trees
Three trees four trees five trees, etc
and you can see so it's kind of nice right you can you can actually create your own and have
Build your own tools to look inside these things and see what's going on
And so we can see here that as you add more and more trees
The accuracy did indeed keep improving or the root mean squared error kept improving although it
That the improvement slowed down
after a while
The
Set is worse and the training set and there's a couple of reasons that could have happened
The first reason could be because we're still overfitting which is not necessarily a problem. This is something we could I did
or maybe it's because the the fact that we're trying to predict the last two weeks is
Actually a problem and that the last two weeks are kind of different to the other
Options in our data set maybe something changed over time
So how do we tell which of those two reasons there are what what is the reason that our validation set is worse?
We can actually find out using a very clever trick called out-of-bag error
oob era, and we use our B error for lots of things you
Can grab the OOBE error?
Well, you can grab the arrow be predictions
From the model with oral-b prediction and you can grab the rmse and you can find that the arrow be error
RSR MSE is
0.21
Which is quite a bit better than 0.2 3
So let me explain what our OB error is
What our be error is is we look at
each
Row of the training set not the validation set each row of the training set and
We say so fix a reset for row. Number one
Which trees?
Included row number one in the training and will say okay. Let's not use those
For calculating the error because it was part of those trees training. I would just
Calculate the error for that row using the trees
Where that row was not included in training that tree because remember every tree is using only a subset of the data
So we do that for every row we find the prediction using only the trees that were not used
That that that row is not used
and those are the Aerobie predictions but other words, this is like giving us a
Validation set result and without actually needing a validation
But the thing is it's not
With that time offset is not looking at the last two weeks
It's looking at the whole training set but this basically tells us how much of the error is
due to
overfitting
Versus Giroux to being the last couple of weeks
So that's a cool trick
Our B error is something that very quickly kind of gives us a sense of how much we're we're overfitting
And we don't even need a validation set to do it
But there's our OB error, so that's telling us a bit about what's going on in our model, um,
Then there's a lot of things we'd like to find out from our model and I've got five things in particular here
Which I generally find pretty interesting
which is
How confident are we?
About our predictions. There's some particular
Prediction we're making like we can say this is what we think the prediction is
But how confident are we is that exactly that or is it just about that or we really have no idea
For particular predicting a particular
item
Which factors were the most important in that prediction and how did they influence it?
Overall, which columns are making the biggest difference in empro. We once could be maybe throw away and it wouldn't matter
Which columns are basically redundant with each other as how we don't really need both of them
And as we vary some column, how does it change the prediction? So those are the five things that work that I'm interested in
Figuring out and we can do all of those things with a random first
Let's start with the first one
the first one we've already seen
that we can
grab all of the predictions
But all of the trees and take their main
To get the actual predictions of the model and then to get the rmse
But what if instead of saying mean we did exactly the same thing?
Like so but instead it said standard deviation
This is going to tell us for every row and our dataset how much did the trees vary and
so if our model really had never seen kind of data like this before it was something where
You know different trees were giving very different predictions. It might give us a sense that maybe
This is something that we're not at all confident about and as you can see when we look at the standard deviation of the trees
For each prediction. Let's just look at the first five. They vary a lot at 0.2 0.1 0.0. Nine point zero point three
Okay
so
this is
A really interesting. It's not something that a lot of people talk about
But I think it's a really interesting approach to kind of figuring out
Whether we might want to be cautious about a particular prediction because maybe we're not very confident about it
There's one thing we can easily do with the random first
the next thing and this is I think the most important thing for me in terms of interpretation is
feature importance
Here's what feature importance looks like we can call feature importance on a model. There's some independent variables
Let's say grab the first ten this says these are the 10
most important features
In this random processes are the things that are the most strongly driving sale price or we could plot them
And so you can see here
There's just a few things that are by far the most important. What year the
Equipment was made bulldozer or whatever. How big is it?
Up, ler system, whatever that means and the product class, whatever that means
and so
You can
Get this by simply looking inside your train model and grabbing the feature importances attribute
And so here for making it better to print out. I'm just sticking that into a data frame and
sorting
ascending by importance
So, how is this actually being done
um
it's it's actually really neat what scikit-learn does and and Ryman the inventor of random forests described is
That you can go through each tree
and then start at the top of the tree and look at each branch and
At each branch see what feature was used the split rich binary
which the binary split was based on which column and then how much better was the model after that split compared to beforehand and
we basically then say okay that column was responsible with that amount of improvement and
so he can add that up across all of the
splits across all of the trees for each column and
then you normalize it so they all add to one and that's what gives you
These numbers which we show the first few of them in this table and the first 30 of them here in this chart
So this is something that's fast and it's easy and it kind of gives us a good sense of like well
maybe the stuff that are less than
0.005
We could remove
So if we did that that would leave us with only 21 columns
So let's try that, let's just but just say okay exes
Which are important the exes which are in this list of ones to keep?
Do the same a valid?
retrain our random forest
and have a look at the result and
Basically, our accuracy is about the same
But we've gone down from 78 columns the 21 color
So I think this is really important
It's not just about
Creating the most accurate model you can but you want to kind of be able to fit it in your head
As best as possible and so 21 columns
it's going to be much easier for us to check that any data issues and understand what's going on and
the accuracy is about the same or the
rmse
So I would say okay, let's do that. Let's just stick with X's important for now on
And so here's this entire set of the 21 features
You can see it looks now like year made and
Product size of the two really important things and then there's a cluster of kind of mainly product related things
That are kind of at the next level of importance
One of the tricky things here is that we've got like
a product class desk model lady
Secondary desk model desk base model a model descriptor. They all look like there might be similar ways of saying the same thing
So one thing that can help us to interpret the feature importance better and understand better. What's happening the model
Is to remove redundant features
So one way to do that is to call faster use cluster columns
which is basically a thin wrapper for stuff that scikit-learn already provides and
What that's going to do is it's going to find pairs of columns
Which are very similar you can see here
So year and sale elapsed see how this line is way out to the right
Or else machine ID and model ID is not at all as way out to the left
But that means that say all year and sale elapsed are
Very very similar when one is lower the other tends to be low and vice versa
here's a group of three which all seem to be much the same and then product group desk and product group and
Then fi best base model and fi model desk
But these all seem like things where maybe we could remove
One of each of these pairs because they're basically aimed to be much the same
You know, they're very, you know, they're when one is higher the other is high and vice versa
So let's try removing one of each of these
Now it takes a little while to train a random forest and so for the just to see whether
Removing something makes it much worse. We could just do a very fast version
So we could just train something where we only have 50,000 rows
per tree
the train for each tree
And we'll just use 40
trees
And let's then just get the arrow B or
So for that fast simple version our basic arrow be with our important X's
0.87 7
And here our be a higher numbers better
So then let's try going through each of the things. We thought we might not need and try dropping them
Then getting the oob error or our exes with that one column removed and so compared to 877
most of them
Don't seem to hurt
Very much
They'll elapsed hurt quite a bit. Alright, so for each of those
Oops, let's go and see which one of the ones seems like we could remove it. But here's the five I found
Move the whole lot and
See what happens and so the oeob went from eight seven seven to eight seven four
There are hardly any difference at all
Despite the fact we managed to get rid of five about variables
So let's create something called X's final which is the X is important and then dropping those five
Save them for later
We can always load them back again
And then let's check our random forest using those and again
Point two three three
Point two three four, so we've got about the same thing, but we've got even less columns now
So we're getting a kind of a simpler and simpler model without hurting our accuracy is great
So the next thing we said we were interested in learning about is but the columns that are particularly the columns that are most important
How does what's the relationship?
Between that column and the dependent variable. Sorry, for example, what's the relationship between product size and sale price?
Now the first thing I would do would be just to look at a histogram
So one way to do that is with a value counts in
pandas
and we can see here our
different
Levels of product size and one thing to note here is actually missing
Is actually the most common and then next most is compact and small and then mini is pretty funny
So we can do the same thing for a year made, I'm now four year made we can't just
See the the basic bar chart here we according to his premise not it's a partial
four year made, we actually need a histogram which
pandas has enough like this built in so we can just call histogram and
That nineteen fifty you remember we created it that's kind of this missing value thing, which used to be a thousand
but most of them seemed to have been
Well into the 90s to thousands
So let's now look at something called a partial dependence plot. I'll show it to you first
here is a
partial dependence plot
Of
Ear made
Against national dependence
What does this mean? Well, we should focus on the part where we actually have a reasonable end of data
So at least well into the 80s
Around here. And so let's look at this bit here. Basically what this says, is that as year made?
increases
the predicted
Sale price log sale price, of course also increases
You can see and the log sale price is increasing linearly on other roughly
So roughly then this is actually an exponential relationship between year made
And sale price. Um
Why do we call it a partial dependence so we're just plotting a kind of the year against the average sale price
well, no, we're not we can't do that because a
Lot of other things change from year to year
Example
Maybe more recently people tend to buy
bigger bulldozers or
more bulldozers with air conditioning or
More expensive models of bulldozers and we really want to be able to say like know just what's the impact of a year and
nothing else and if you think about it from a kind of a
inflation point of view
You would expect that
Older bulldozers would be kind of
Like that bulldozers would get a kind of a constant ratio
Cheaper the further you go back which is what we see. So what we really want to say is all other things being equal
what happens if only the year changes and
There's a really cool way. We can answer that question with a random forest
So how does year made impact sale price all other things being equal?
What we can do is we can go into an actual data set and replace every single value in the year made column
with 1950 and then can calculate the predicted sale price for every single option and
then take the average over all the options and that's what gives us this value here and
Then we can do the same for 1951 19 2 and so forth until eventually we get to our final year of 2011
So this isolates the effect of only year made
So it's a kind of a bit of a curious thing to do but it's actually it's a pretty neat trick
But trying to kind of pull apart and create this
Partial dependence say what might be the impact of just changing your maid
And we can do the same thing for product size
And one of the interesting things if we do it for product sizes, we see that the lowest
value of
predicted sale price log sale price is
N/a
Which is a bit of a worry
because we kind of want to know well that means it's really important the question of whether or not the product size is labeled is
really important and
That is something that I would want to dig into before
I actually use this model to find out well, why is it that sometimes things aren't labeled and what does it mean?
you know, why is it that that's actually that's just
important predictor
So that is the partial dependence pot and it's so really pepper brick
So we have looked at four of the five questions we said we wanted to answer at the start of this section
so the last one that we want to answer is
One here we're predicting with a particular row of data
What were the most important factors and how did they influence that predict?
This is quite related to the very first thing we saw so it's like imagine you were using this
Auction price model in real life you had something on your tablet and you went into some auction and you looked up what the predicted
auction price would be for this lot that's coming up to find out whether
It seems like it's being under or overvalued and then you decide what to do about that
So one thing we said we'd be interested to know is like well are we actually confident in our prediction and
Then we might be curious to find out like oh, I'm really surprised. It was predicting such a high value
Why was it predicting such a high value?
So who find the answer to that question?
We can use a module cord tree interpreter
and trie interpreter
The way it works is that you pass in a
Single row so it's like here's the oxygen that's coming up. Here's the model. Here's the auctioneer ID cetera et cetera
please predict the
value
From the random forest. What's the expected sale price?
and then what we can do is we can take that one row of data and put it through the first decision tree and
We can see what's the first split that's selected and then based on that split
Does it end up increasing or decreasing the predicted?
price compared to that kind of raw baseline model
we've just take the average and then you can do that again at the next bit and again at the next bit and the
Expert so for each split we see what the increase or decrease in
the
Diction that's not right. We see what the increase or decrease in the prediction is
Except while I'm here
Compared to the parent node, and so then do that for every tree and then add up the total change and importance by variable
And that allows you to draw something like this
so here's something that's looking at one particular row of data and
overall
We start at zero and so 0 is
The initial
Endpoint 1 remember this number 10.1 is the average
Log sale price of the whole data set they call it the bias B interpreter. And so if we call that 0
Then for this particular row we're looking at
ear made as a negative for point to impact on the prediction and then
Product size has a positive point, too
Plus system has a positive 0.046 model ID has a positive 0.127
And so forth right and so the red ones are negative and the green ones are positive and you can see how they all join
Up until eventually overall
The prediction is that it's going to be negative point one to two compared to
ten point one
which is equal to
Point nine eight
So this kind of plot is called a waterfall plot
And so basically when we say tree interpret or predict it gives us back the
Prediction which
Number we get back from the random forest the bias
Which is just always this ten point one for this data set and then the contributions
Which is all of these different values. It's how much how important was each
factor and here I've used a threshold, which means
Anything that was less than 0.08 or gets thrown into this other
A degree. I think this is a really useful kind of thing to have in production
Because it can help you answer questions whether it will be to the customer or for you know
Whoever's using your model if they're surprised about some fiction. Why is that prediction?
So I'm going to show you something
really interesting
using some synthetic data and
I want you to really have a think about
Why this is happening
Before I tell you oh, and I pause the video if you're watching the video
When I get to that point, um, let's start by creating. Um, some synthetic data like so so we're going to grab
40 values evenly spaced between 0 and 20 and
Then we're just going to create the y equals x line
and add
some
normally distributed random jitter on that
Here's the scatter plot
So here's some data we want to try and predict if we're going to use a random forest
You know kind of a bit of a overkill here
Now in this case, we only have one independent variable
Scikit-learn expects is to have more than one
So we can use
Unscrews in pi torch to add that go from a shape of 40 in other words a vector with 40 elements
To a shape of 40 comma 1 in other words a matrix of 40 rows with one column, but this unscrews one
Means at a unit axis here
I don't use on squeeze very often because I actually generally prefer the index with a special value none
this works in pi torch and none pay and
This work the way it works is to say okay, excellent. Remember that size is a vector of length 40 every row and
Then none means insert a unit axis here on so these are two ways of doing the same thing
But this one is a little bit more flexible. So that's what I use more often. But now that we've got
The shape that is expected which is a back to tensor and a row or an array with two dimensions or axes
We can create a random forest
We can fit it and let's just use the first 30 data points and it's so kind of top here
And then let's do a prediction, all right, so let's plot the original data points and then also plot a prediction
and look what happens on the prediction it acts it's kind of nice and accurate and
then suddenly
What happens? Yes, this is the bit where if you watch in the video, I want you to pause and never think biases flat
So what's going on here
well
remember a random forest is just taking the average of predictions of a bunch of trees and
a tree the prediction of a tree is just
The average of the values in a leaf node
And remember we fitted using a training set containing only the first 30
So none of these appeared in the training set, so the highest we could get would be the average of
values that are inside the training set in other words says this maximum we can get to
So random forests cannot extrapolate
outside of the bounds of the data that they've training set
This is going to be a huge problem for things like time series prediction where there's like an underlying trend for instance
but really
It's more about general issue than just time variables
it's going to be hard for rent or
Impossible often for random for us to just extrapolate outside the types of data that it's seen in a general sense
So we need to make sure that our validation set not contain
output domain data
So, how do we find out of domain data?
So we might not even know if our test set is
Distributed in the same way as our training data, so if they're from two different time periods, how do you kind of tell?
How they vary right or if it's a cattle competition. How do you tell if the test set and the training set?
Which Cargill gives you have some underlying differences?
Is actually a cool trick you can do which is you can create a column chord is valid
Contains zero for everything in the training set and one for everything in the validations that
It's concatenating all of the independent variables together
So it's so so it's coordinating the independent variables for both the training and validation set together
So this is our independent variable
And this becomes our dependent variable and we're going to create a random forest, not for predicting price
But a random forest that predicts is this row from the validation set or the training set
The validation set in the training set are from kind of the same distribution if they're not different
Then this random forest should basically have zero
predictive power
If it has any predictive power
Then it means that our training and validations that are different and to find out the source of that difference we can use
feature importance
And so you can see here that the difference between the validation set and the training set
Is not surprisingly sale elapsed. So that's the number of days since I think like 1970 or something
So it's basically the date
Oh, yes, of course
you can predict whether something is in the
Validation set or the training set by looking at the date because that's actually how to find them. That makes sense
This is interesting sales ID
so it looks like the sales ID is not some random identifier, but it increases over time and
ditto for machine ID
And then there's some other smaller ones here that kind of makes sense
So I guess for something like model desk. I guess there are certain models that were only made in later years for instance
Can see these top three columns are a bit of an issue
So then we could say like okay what happens if we look at each one of those columns those first three and remove them
and then see
Now it changes our our MSC on our
Sales price model on the validation set we start from point two three two
Removing sales ID
Actually makes it a bit better
They'll elapsed makes it a bit worse machine ID about the same
But we can probably remove sales ID and machine ID without losing any accuracy and yep
it's actually slide improve but most importantly it's going to be more resilient over time, right because we're trying to remove the
time-related features
Another thing to note is that since it seems that you know
This kind of sale elapsed issue that maybe it's making a big difference is maybe looking at the sale year
Distribution this is the histogram
Most of the sales are in the last few years anyway
Now what happens if we only include the most recent few years, let's just include everything after 20 2004
So that is exes filtered
And if I trained on that subset
Then my accuracy goes improves a bit more from to be three one
three three Oh
So that's interesting, right?
We're actually using less data less rows and getting a slightly better result because the more recent data is more representative
So that's about as far as we can get with our random forest, but what I will say is this
this issue of extrapolation
Would not happen
with a neuro net but it because a neural net is using the kind of the underlying layers are linear layers and
So linear layers can absolutely extrapolate
So the obvious thing to think then at this point is well
Maybe but a neural net there a better job of this that's gonna be the thing next up to this question a question first
how do
How does feature importance relate to correlation?
Which importance doesn't particularly relate to a correlation
Correlation is a concept for linear models. And this is not a linear model
so remember feature importance is calculated by looking at the
Improvement in accuracy as you go down each tree and you go down each binary spit
If you're used to linear regression then I guess our relation sometimes can be used as a measure of
Importance but this is a much more kind of direct version
it's
taking account of these
Nonlinearities and interactions as well. So it's a much more
a
flexible and reliable measure and release picture importance
any more question
So do the same thing with a neural network
I'm going to just copy and paste the same lines of code that I had
from before but this time I call it n n D F n n and these are the same lines of code and
I'll grab the same list of columns we had before in the dependent variable to get the same data frame
Now as we've discussed four categorical columns, we probably want to use embeddings so to create embeddings
To know which columns should be treated as categorical variables and as we discussed we can use Conte cats bit for that
One of the useful things we can pass that is the maximum cardinality
So max card equals nine thousand means if there's a column with more than nine thousand levels
You should treat it as continuous and if it's got less than nine thousand levels rigid as categorical
So that's you know, it's a simple little function that just checks the cardinality and splits them based on how many discrete levels they have
and of course it their data type if it's not
Actually a numeric data type it has to be categorical
So there's our
There's a speed
And then
From there, what we can do is we can say oh
We've got to be a bit careful of sale lapsed because actually sale elapsed I think has less than nine thousand categories
But we definitely don't want to use that as a categorical variable
The whole point was to make it that this is something that we can extrapolate are we certainly anything? That's kind of I'm dependent
Oh, you think that we might see things outside the range of inputs?
in the
Training data we should make them
Continuous variables. So let's make sale elapse to put it in continuous neural net and remove it from
categorical
So here's the number of unique levels this is from pandas for everything in our neural net data set for the categorical variables and
I get a bit nervous when I see these really high numbers
So I don't want to have too many things with like lots and lots of categories
The reason I don't want lots of things with lots and lots of categories is just they got to take up a lot of parameters
Because you know embedding matrix. This is you know, every one of these is a row in an embedding mech in
This case I notice model ID and model desk might be describing something very similar
so it quite like to find out if I could get rid of one and
An easy way to do that would be to use a random forest
So let's try removing
the
model desk
and
Let's create a random forest
See what happens and oh, it's actually a tiny bit better and certainly not worse
So that suggests that we can actually get rid of one of these levels or one of these variables
So let's get rid of that one
So now we can create a tabular panda's object just like before
But this time we're going to add one more
processor which is normalized and
The reason we need normalize so normalize is subtract the mean divided by the standard deviation
We didn't need that for a random post because for a random forest
We're just looking at less than or greater then through our binary splits
So all that matters is the order of things how they're sorted doesn't matter whether they're super big or super small
But it definitely matters for neural nets because we have these linear layers
So we don't want to have
You know things with kind of crazy distributions with some super big numbers and super small numbers is it's not going to work
So it's always a good idea to normalize things here on it's where we can do that in a tabular
Zero net by using the normalize a typical approach
So we can do the same thing that we did before with creating our tabular pandas
That bill object the neural net
And then we can create data loaders
From that with a batch size and this is a large batch size because tabular models
don't generally require nearly as much CPU RAM as a
Convolutional neural net or something or an iron or something?
Since it regression model we're going to want our range. So let's find the minimum and maximum of our dependent variable
This and then we can now go ahead and create a tabular Lerner
But a temple alone is going to take outdated loaders our way range
How many?
Activations. Do you want in each of the linear layers? And so you can have as many linear layers as you like? Yeah
I'm how many outputs are there. This is a regression with a single output and what loss function do you want?
We can use LR find
And then we can go ahead and use pet one cycle
There's no pre trained model, obviously because this is not something where people have got pre train models for
Industrial equipment options, we just use fit one cycle and
train for a minute
We can check and our our MSE is 0.2
2x
Which here? It was 0.23. Oh, but that's amazing
We actually have you know straight away a better result and the random first. It's a little more fussy
It took something takes a little bit longer
and as you can see, you know for
Interesting data sets like this we can get some great results
with neural nets
So here's something else we could do
The random forest in the neural net. They each have their own pros and cons as something sacred atomism. They're less good
So maybe we can get the best of both worlds and a really easy way to do that is to use
Ensemble, we've already seen that a random forest is a decision tree ensemble
But how we can put that into another ensemble you can have an ensemble of the random forest and you're on it
There's lots of super fancy ways
You can do that had a really simple way is to take the average
so sum up the predictions from the two models by bow to
Use that as a prediction so that's our ensemble prediction is just literally the average of the random forest prediction and the neuron a prediction
And that gives us pointer to three
This is point two to six
So how good is that?
well
It's a little hard to say because unfortunately this
Competition is old enough that we can't even submit to it and find out how we would have gone on cackle
so we don't really know and so we're relying on our own validations that
But it's quite a bit better than even the first place score on the test set
So if the validation set is
You know
Doing a good job. Then this is a good sign that this is a really really good model
which wouldn't necessarily be that surprising, um, because you know in the last few years I
guess we've learned a lot about
building these kinds of models and
we're kind of taking advantage of a lot of the tricks that have that have appeared in recent years and
Yeah, maybe this goes to show that well
I think it certainly goes to show at both random forests and neural nets have a lot offer and
Try both and maybe even find both
We've talked about an approach to ensemble in court bagging
which is where we train lots of models on different subsets of the data like the average of
Another approach to ensemble in to Cleon fumbling of trees is called boosting
and boosting involves training a
Small model which under fits your data set, but maybe like just have a very small number of if notes
Then you calculate the predictions using the small model
And then you subtract the predictions from the targets
So these are kind of like the errors of your small under fit model. We call them residual
and
Then go back to step one, but now instead of using the original targets
Use the residuals the Train a small model which under fits your dataset attempting to predict
residuals
Again in in until you reach some stopping criterion such as the maximum number of trees
Now you that will leave you with a bunch of models, which you don't average
But which use some?
Because each one is creating a model that's based on the residual of the previous one
So we've subtracted the predictions of each new tree from the residuals of the previous tree
But the residuals get smaller and smaller and then to make predictions
We just have to do the opposite which is to add them all together
So there's lots of variants of this
But you'll see things like gbms or gradient boosted machines or GB TTS for gradient boosted decision trees
and there's lots and
Minor details surround, you know, and they're insignificant details
But the basic idea is is what I've shown to question. All right, let's take the questions
They're dropping features in a model as a way to reduce the complexity of the model and thus reduce overfitting
Is this better than adding some regularization like weight decay a Bueller? I
Didn't claim that removed columns to avoid overfitting
We remove the columns to simplify here are things analyze and then
It should also mean we don't need as many trees but there's no particular reason to believe that this will regular raise and
Well, the idea of regularization doesn't necessarily make a lot of sense to random forests and always add more trees
is
There a good heuristic for picking the number of linear layers in the tabular model
Not really well if there is I don't know what it is
I guess
sir
Three hidden layers works pretty well
So, you know what I showed
Those numbers I showed her
Pretty good for a large ish model
A default is as 200 and 100. So maybe start with the default and then got
502 50 if that ends an improvement and like just keep doubling them
And ups improving or you run out of memory odd, huh?
Anything to note about boosted models is that there's nothing to stop us from overfitting you add more and more trees
The bagging model sort of a random forest. It's going to get going to generalize better and better as your each time
You're using your model, which is based on a subset of the day
But boosting
Each model will fit the training set better and better
virtually over fit or in law, so
roasting methods do require journaling I parameter tuning and fiddling around with
You know you certainly have regularization
Listing they're pretty sensitive to their hyper parameters, which is why they're not normally much first quarter
They they often they more often when cattle competition
Random forests do like they tend to be good at getting that last little bit of performance
But the last thing I'm going to mention is something super neat which a lot of people don't seem to know
Exists. There's a Shang's at super core, which is something from the entity embeddings paper
The table from it where what they did was they built a neural network?
they got the entity embeddings ee
And then they try to random forest using the entity embedding as predictors
The approach I described with just the Royal categorical variables and the the error for a random forest went from
0.16
0.11 a huge improvement and
Very simple method K and N and from point two nine to 0.1 one basically all of the methods when they used entity embeddings
Suddenly improved a lot
the one thing you you should try if you have a look at the further research section after the questionnaire is
it asks to try to
Do this actually take those entity embeddings that we trained in the neural net and use them in the random post
and then maybe try on some bowling again and see if you can beat the
point root to three
That we had this is a really nice idea
It's like you get you know, all the benefits of we've boosted decision trees
but all of the nice features of entity embeddings
And so this is something that not enough people tend to be playing with for some reason
So overall
You know random forests are nice and easy to train, you know, they're very resilient they don't require much pre-processing they're trained quickly
They don't over fit
You know, they can be a little less accurate and
They can be a bit slow at inference time because for inference you have to go through every one of those trees
Having said that a binary tree and be pretty heavily optimized
though
You know, it is something you can basically create a totally compiled version of a tree and they can certainly also be done entirely
In parallel
So that's something to consider. Um
Radiant boosting machines are also fast to train on the hole but a little more fussy about hyper parameters
You have to be careful about overfitting
But get more accurate
Neural nets may be the fussiest to deal with they've kind of got the least
Rules of thumb around or tutorials around saying this is and how to do it
It's just a bit a bit newer a little bit less. Well, understood
But they can give better results in many
Situations than the other two approaches or at least with an ensemble can improve the other two approaches?
So I would always start with a random fire
And then see if you can beat it using these
So, yeah, why don't you now see if you can find a cable competition with tabular data whether it's running now
It's a past one and see if you can repeat this process
For that and see if you can get in the top and percent if the private leaderboard that would be a really great
stretch goal at this point
Implement the decision tree algorithm yourself. I think that's an important one
Do you really understand it and then from there create your own random forests from scratch. You might be surprised. It's not that hard
Look at the tabular model source code and at this point, this is pretty exciting. You should find you pretty much though
What all the lines do with two exceptions?
And if you don't, you know dig around and explore an experiment and see if you can figure it out
And with that we are
I am very excited to say at a point where we've really dug all the way into the end of these
real valuable effective
Fast AI applications and we're understanding what's going on inside them
What should we expect for next week?
Oh next week we will at NLP and division
The same kind of idea is no the old deep to see what's going on
Thanks everybody see you next week